Guide to the Albert and Celia Steward Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Albert and Celia Steward Papers
1908-1979
RG 20
Yale University Divinity School Library
7.5
(16 boxes)
The papers document the Steward's missionary work and personal lives, detailing their daily activities and political and social conditions in China. Albert Newton Steward (1897-1959) and Celia Belle Speak Steward (1897-1992) were stationed in Nanking, China as educational missionaries under the Methodist Board of Missions. Albert taught botany at the University of Nanking. During World War II, Albert was interned at Chapei Camp, Shanghai from 1943-1945. In 1951, Albert became curator of the Herbarium and professor at Oregon State College.
Steward, Albert Newton, 1897-
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Steward family.
Biographical / Historical
1897 Albert Newton Steward born in California
1897 Celia Belle Speak born in Kentucky
1918 ANS and CSS married (Children: Margaret, 1919; Newton, 1920; Leland, 1922; Virginia, 1924; Ruth, 1937; David, 1938)
1921 ANS - B.S. from Oregon Agricultural College
1921-1926 Stationed in Nanking as educational missionaries under the Methodist Board of Missions; ANS taught botany at University of Nanking.
1926-1930 On extended furlough in U.S.; ANS received Ph.D. in Biology from Harvard
1930-1937 Stationed in Nanking
1932 Celia's mother, Sarah Speak, on year long visit to China
1937 Aug Family evacuated from China
1938 Sep ANS returned to China; CSS and children remained in California
1939Jul CSS and three younger children returned to China
1941 Jan CSS and children returned to U.S.; ANS stayed in Nanking
1942 fall ANS living in Shanghai
1943 Feb ANS interned at Chapei Camp, Shanghai
1945 Sep ANS released from internment camp; remained in China to look after affairs of University of Nanking
1946 Mar ANS returned to U.S.
1947 Aug ANS, CSS, Ruth and David to China
1948 Nov Ruth and David returned to U.S.
1949 Oct CSS returned to U.S.
1950 Sep ANS returned to U.S.; family lived in Auburndale, MA while ANS worked on Manual of Vascular Plants of the Lower Yangtze Valley (published 1958) at Harvard's Arnold Arboretum under Guggenheim grant.
1951 ANS became curator of Herbarium and professor at Oregon State College.
1959 Jun ANS died
1967 CSS chosen Oregon Mother-of-the-Year
1979 CSS entered nursing home in Oregon
1990 CSS died
Scope and Contents
The missionary work and personal lives of Albert and Celia Steward are well documented in these papers. Based at the University of Nanking, Albert Steward combined devotion to science, Christian outreach to students, and community involvement in his active missionary service in China. Celia Steward's years in China, though defined to a significant degree by her devotion to her six children, were notable for her openness to the Chinese people and her efforts to improve the lives of people, particularly of women, in China. Celia used her skills of cooking, sewing, singing, teaching, typing and entertaining to interact with the Chinese people and with fellow missionaries, and to aid her husband in his work. More so than many missionaries, the Stewards opened their home to the Chinese and developed longstanding relationships with students and colleagues.
The Stewards maintained close ties with their families in the United States and sent regular, detailed letters which describe their daily activities and political and social conditions in China. Albert's experience in the Japanese internment camp of Chapei is well documented, as is the period following the Communist takeover in Nanking. The Stewards also retained in their files many invitations, notes, programs and other ephemeral documents which provide insight into the flow and tone of daily missionary life.
The Steward Papers are complemented by various other collections held at the Yale Divinity School Library. Extensive files documenting the University of Nanking in Record Group No. 11, include additional correspondence and writings of Albert Steward. The Library also holds papers of the Hayes family, Bates family and other close missionary friends of the Stewards. Taken in conjunction, these sources provide excellent insight into the missionary community and modes of mission in Nanking during the 1920s through 1950.
Series I, Correspondence, includes family correspondence, circular letters sent out by the Stewards, correspondence with Western colleagues and with Chinese colleagues and students. The early part of the Stewards' service in China is most thoroughly documented in letters sent to the extended family; by the 1940s the older Steward children were living in the United States and received the most detailed letters. Regular circular letters sent by the Stewards provide a convenient overview of their experiences. Samples of family correspondence from the period after 1950 have been retained in the collection.
The second series, Writings, Talks, includes material ranging from formal reflections on the Stewards' missionary experience to scientific writings by Albert to notes for numerous talks. Both Celia and Albert were clearly popular speakers before churches and civic groups while in the United States. The presentations they made to these groups provide interesting evaluation and anecdotal documentation of their work in China. The documented interaction between the Stewards and the church groups in the U.S. which supported them also provides insight into the impact of the missionary movement upon American religious life.
Series III, Subject File, includes an interesting variety of material, primarily collected in China. Of particular interest are the materials related to the Communist takeover in China, materials related to Nanking, and documentation of the Saturday Evening Group held for Chinese students and colleagues in the Stewards' home.
Series IV, Biographical Material, provides very thorough documentation of the background and lives of the Stewards. A couple of papers written by students about Celia Steward are included, as well as a wealth of documentation prepared at the time of her selection as Oregon Mother-of-the-Year.
Series V, Photographs, includes relatively few items documenting the Steward family. Photographs related to the University of Nanking in Record Group No. 11 would supplement those available in this collection. Addendum: four cases of slides used by the Stewards in presentations to churches about mission work in China.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1908-1979
II. Writings, Talks, 1930-1959
III. Subject File, 1933-1950
IV. Biographical Material, 1913-1977, n.d.
V. Photographs, 1934-1946, n.d.
Concentration camps -- China; Missions -- China; Missionaries; Steward, Albert Newton, 1897-; Steward, Celia Speak; Methodist Episcopal Church -- Missions -- China; Methodist Episcopal Church. Board of Foreign Missions
- Correspondence, 1908-1979; Series I
  - Family Correspondence
    - Albert to/from Celia, 1931-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Celia to Albert, 1941 -1950 (Box 16, Folder 281-301)
    - Albert to Celia, 1941- 1950 (Box 16, Folder 302-320)
    - Summary of Celia's letters to Albert (1941-1950) (Box 16, Folder 321)
    - Summary of Albert's letters to Celia (1941-1950) (Box 16, Folder 322)
    - Albert / Celia, 1946-1957, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Albert, Celia to/from their children, 1931-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5-21)
    - Albert, Celia to/from their children, 1950-1976,n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Albert, Celia to/from extended family, 1910,1918-1931 (Box 2, Folder 23-42)
    - Albert, Celia to/from extended family, 1932 -1950, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 43-66)
    - Other Speak/Steward family correspondence, 1908-1976 (Box 4, Folder 67-72)
    - Other correspondence of Sarah Speak, mother of Celia, 1922-1934,n.d. (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Circular letters sent out by Albert and Celia Steward
    - Circular letters, 1924,1931-1950 (Box 4, Folder 74-83)
    - Circular letters, 1951-1977 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - General Correspondence: Western Colleagues and Acquaintances
    - A (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Anderson, Hilda, 1938-1948 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Atwood, W. M. B, 1931-1950 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Baldwin, Raymond and Rachel, 1948-1979 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Bates, Miner Searle, 1949-1950,n.d (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Bauer, Grace, 1939-1946 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Buck, J. Lossing, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - C (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - China Christian Educational Association, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - D (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Daniels, J. Horton, 1944-1950 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - DeVol, Charles E., 1934-1958 (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - E,F (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - G (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Gale, Frank and Ailie, 1941-1949 (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - Gilkey, Helen, 1919-1941 (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Gilkey, Helen, 1942-1950 (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Gilkey, Helen, 1951-1962 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Guggenheim Foundation H, 1951-1954 (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Hale, Elizabeth, 1947-1951 (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - Hayes, Paul and Helen, 1937-1950 (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Henderson, Aurelie, 1947-1949 (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Humphrey family, 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - Illick, Theron and Bernice J, 1943-1958 (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - Jones, Lucile and Francis, 1942-1954 (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - Jones, Tracey K., Jr. (see also: Methodist Church, Board of Missions), 1948 (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - K (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - L (Box 5, Folder 111)
    - Lacy, Creighton and Frances, 1949-1951 (Box 5, Folder 112)
    - M (Box 5, Folder 113)
    - McCain, Pearle, 1949-1951 (Box 5, Folder 114)
    - Methodist Church, Board of Missions, 1937-1945 (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - Methodist Church, Board of Missions, 1947-1949 (Box 5, Folder 116)
    - Methodist Church, Board of Missions, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 117)
    - Methodist Church, Board of Missions, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 118)
    - Methodist Church, Board of Missions, 1952-1955 (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - Methodist Church, Board of Missions, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - Mills, W. Plumer, 1942-1948 (Box 6, Folder 121)
    - Moffet, Anna, 1938-1944 (Box 6, Folder 122)
    - N,O (Box 6, Folder 123)
    - Oregon Agricultural College, 1921-1925 (Box 6, Folder 124)
    - Oregon State College, 1947-1959 (Box 6, Folder 125)
    - P (Box 6, Folder 126)
    - Poo Shan Tong Relief Association, Nanking, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 127)
    - Price, P. Frank, 1941-1949 (Box 6, Folder 128)
    - Priest, Elsie R, 1938-1956 (Box 6, Folder 129)
    - Rouse, Marguerite, 1936-1950 (Box 6, Folder 131)
    - S (Box 6, Folder 132)
    - Slocum, Burl and Esther, 1932-1962 (Box 6, Folder 133)
    - Smith, Dorothy and Stanley, 1943-1948,n.d (Box 6, Folder 134)
    - Stuart, J. Leighton, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 135)
    - Supporting churches and women's groups in U.S. (Box 6, Folder 136)
    - T (Box 6, Folder 137)
    - Thompson, May Bel, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 138)
    - Trimmer, Peter and Ruth, 1938-1959 (Box 6, Folder 139)
    - U (Box 6, Folder 140)
    - United Board for Christian Colleges in China/ United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia, 1949-1958 (Box 6, Folder 141)
    - Upham, Ethel, 1947-1951 (Box 6, Folder 142)
    - V,W (Box 6, Folder 143)
    - Ward, Ralph A. and Mildred, 1942-1956 (Box 6, Folder 144)
    - Watters, Hyla, 1939-1950,n.d. (Box 6, Folder 145)
    - Wharton, Joseph, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 146)
    - Whitmer, Harriet, 1944-1951 (Box 6, Folder 147)
    - Wolcott, Jessie, 1946-1950 (Box 6, Folder 148)
    - World Peace Committee, First Methodist Church Corvallis, Oregon, 1956-1959 (Box 6, Folder 149)
    - Y (Box 6, Folder 150)
    - Yale Divinity School Library - China Records Project, 1968-1972 (Box 6, Folder 151)
    - first names and unidentified (Box 6, Folder 151)
  - General Correspondence: Chinese Colleagues and Acquaintances
    - Ahn - Cheng (Box 6, Folder 153)
    - Cheo - Chow (Box 6, Folder 154)
    - Dang (Box 7, Folder 155)
    - Dju - Feng (Box 7, Folder 156)
    - Gee (Box 7, Folder 157)
    - Han - Hsia (Box 7, Folder 158)
    - Hsu - Hu (Box 7, Folder 159)
    - Huang (Box 7, Folder 160)
    - Jen - Lin (Box 7, Folder 161)
    - Ling - Ren (Box 7, Folder 162)
    - Shih - Sie (Box 7, Folder 163)
    - Teng - Tsao (Box 7, Folder 164)
    - Wang (Box 7, Folder 165)
    - Wei, C.T. - Wu, Blanche (Box 7, Folder 166)
    - Wu Yi-Fang - Zau, given names only (Box 7, Folder 167)
  - Topical File of Correspondence
    - China era: corres. with agencies and companies (Box 7, Folder 169)
    - China era: invitations (Box 7, Folder 170)
    - China era: short notes from missionary colleagues (Box 7, Folder 171)
    - China era: short notes from Chinese colleagues and acquaintances (Box 7, Folder 172)
    - Corres. with miscellaneous non-Chinese foreign students (Box 7, Folder 168)
- Writings, Talks, 1930-1959; Series II
  - Jointly Written by Albert and Celia Steward
    - "Our First Missionary Journey" (Box 8, Folder 173)
  - Written by Celia Steward
    - "Incidents and Impressions from Nanking", 1949 (Box 8, Folder 174)
    - Miscellaneous short writings, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 175)
    - Talks, 1934-1939 (Box 8, Folder 176)
  - Written by Albert Steward
    - "California to Szechuan" (second copy in Box 16, Folder 323), 1938 (Box 8, Folder 179)
    - re. Manual of the Vascular Plants of the Lower Yangtze Valley (Box 8, Folder 180)
    - "Oregon Gardens 100 Years Ago", 1959 (Box 8, Folder 181)
    - "The Polygoneae of Eastern Asia", 1930 (Box 8, Folder 182)
    - "Vascular Plants of the Lower Yangtze Valley- II Spermatophyta" (typescript), 1950 (Box 8, Folder 183)
    - Brief scientific articles (Box 8, Folder 184)
    - Miscellaneous short writings, 1945-1957 (Box 8, Folder 185)
    - Notes for talks re. Communism in China (Box 8, Folder 186)
    - Notes for talks re. agriculture, rural work (Box 8, Folder 187)
    - Notes for talks re. world peace (Box 8, Folder 188)
    - Notes for talks - miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 189, 190)
  - Written by others
    - Written by Newton Steward, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 191)
    - Short writings, authors unidentified (Box 8, Folder 192)
- Subject File, 1933-1950; Series III
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Agriculture, food in China Agriculture, food in China (Box 9, Folder 193)
  - Berkeley, CA - Old China Hands roster, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 194)
  - Blind in China (Box 9, Folder 195)
  - Canton, bombing of, 1938 (Box 9, Folder 196)
  - Chiang Kai-shek (Box 9, Folder 197)
  - Chiang Kai-shek, Madame (Soong Mei-ling) (Box 9, Folder 198)
  - China - map, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 199)
  - China - post 1960 (Box 9, Folder 200)
  - Chinese language material (Box 9, Folder 201)
  - Chinese-Soviet Friendship Association, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 202)
  - Chinese theater (Box 9, Folder 203)
  - Christian higher education in China (Box 9, Folder 204)
  - Citizens Committee to Repeal Chinese Exclusion, ca. 1943 (Box 9, Folder 205)
  - Committee on American Principles and Fair Play, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 206)
  - Communist takeover in China -general, 1949-1951 (Box 9, Folder 207)
  - Communist takeover in China -impact on Christian activity, 1948-1951 (Box 9, Folder 208)
  - Communist takeover in China -Chinese periodicals, 1949-1950 (Box 9, Folder 209)
  - Communist takeover in China -propaganda posters (Box 9, Folder 210)
  - Cooperative forest at Ch'ing Lung Shan, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 211)
  - Feng Yu Hsiang (Box 9, Folder 212)
  - Gilkey, Helen (Box 9, Folder 213)
  - Hillcrest School (Nanking American School), 1934 (Box 9, Folder 214)
  - Internment of missionaries by Japanese (Box 9, Folder 215)
  - Kuling American School Laubach, Frank C., 1935 (Box 10, Folder 216)
  - Methodist missions in China, 1936-1950 (Box 10, Folder 218)
  - Missionaries returning from China, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 219)
  - Nanking-conditions during Sino-Japanese war (Box 10, Folder 220)
  - Nanking-cultural events, opportunities, 1934-1949,n.d. (Box 10, Folder 221)
  - Nanking-description of, map, 1933, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 222)
  - Nanking-Christian missions in (Box 10, Folder 223)
  - Nanking Foreign Cemetery (Box 10, Folder 224)
  - Nanking Union Church (Box 10, Folder 225)
  - Nanking, University of -audio-visual education (Box 10, Folder 226)
  - Nanking, University of-College of Agriculture and Forestry (Box 10, Folder 227)
  - Nanking, University of -miscellaneous (Box 10, Folder 228)
  - Nanking, University of -newsletters, 1937-1946 (Box 10, Folder 229)
  - Nanking, University of -religious life, 1937,1950 (Box 10, Folder 230)
  - Plants in China (Box 10, Folder 231)
  - Rural work in China, 1931,1950 (Box 10, Folder 232)
  - Saturday Evening Student Group - held at Stewards' home (Box 10, Folder 233)
  - Shanghai - refugees, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 234)
  - Shaw, Ella C. (Box 10, Folder 235)
  - Silkworms (Box 10, Folder 236)
  - Women in China, 1937,1945 (Box 10, Folder 237)
  - Yenching University, survey of religious life, 1936-1937 (Box 10, Folder 238)
  - Ephemeral collected material (Box 10, Folder 239)
- Biographical Material, 1913-1977, n.d; Series IV
  - Related to ANS and/or CSS and Children
    - Address books, lists, calling cards (Box 10, Folder 240)
    - Documentation of life in Nanking, 1945-1950,n.d. (Box 10, Folder 241)
    - Financial records (Box 11, Folder 242)
    - Medical records (Box 11, Folder 243, 244)
    - Passports, birth certificates (Box 11, Folder 245)
    - Records of guests in Steward home (Box 11, Folder 246)
    - Records of guests in Steward home (Box 12, Folder 247)
    - Records of mail, packages sent/received, 1948,1959 (Box 12, Folder 248)
    - Travels to/from China (Box 12, Folder 249)
    - Travels in United States (Box 12, Folder 250)
  - Related to ANS
    - Appointment book, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 251)
    - Autograph book, ca.1913 (Box 12, Folder 251)
    - Autobiographical/biographical statements (Box 12, Folder 252)
    - Biographical newspaper clippings (Box 12, Folder 253)
    - Citations, awards, certificates (Box 12, Folder 254)
    - Education, research and writing grants (Box 12, Folder 255)
    - Internment by Japanese (Box 12, Folder 256)
    - List of scientific publications (Box 13, Folder 257)
    - Oregon State College years (Box 13, Folder 258)
    - Search for employment (Box 13, Folder 259)
  - Related to CSS
    - Autobiographical/biographical statements (Box 13, Folder 260)
    - Biographical newspapers clippings (Box 13, Folder 261)
    - Birthday book (Box 13, Folder 262)
    - Selection as Oregon Mother-of-the-Year, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 263, 264)
  - Related to Children of ANS and CSS
    - David Steward (Box 13, Folder 265)
    - Leland Steward (Box 13, Folder 266)
    - Margaret Steward (Box 13, Folder 267)
    - Newton Steward (Box 13, Folder 268)
    - Ruth Steward (Box 13, Folder 269)
    - Virginia Steward (Box 13, Folder 270)
  - Related to Grandchildren of ANS and CSS
    - Misc. (Box 13, Folder 271)
  - Related to Parents of ANS and CSS
    - Misc. (Box 13, Folder 272)
- Photographs, 1934-1946, n.d.; Series V
  - Family Photographs (Box 13, Folder 273)
  - "Graduates of Ginling College", 1934 (Box 13, Folder 274)
  - "Farewell to Bates and Sone, International Relief Committee", 1941 (Box 13, Folder 275)
  - "Students of University of Nanking school to train rural workers", 1941 (Box 13, Folder 276)
  - "Child Welfare Project, Bible Teachers' Training School, Nanking", n.d. (Box 13, Folder 277)
  - Chinese Colleagues, 1940-1946, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 278)
  - Scenes in China, incl. cotton mill in Shanghai, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 279)
  - Photos from Audio-visual education dept., University of Nanking (Box 13, Folder 280)
  - Lantern slides (2 cases; approx. 70 slides) Scenes from throughout China, incl. Peking, Nanking, Shanghai; countryside and city scenes (Box 14)
  - Lantern Slides (1 case; approx. 50 slides) Miscellaneous scenes in China (Box 15)
  - 35 mm slides (1 case; 27 slides) Slides and accompanying booklet "West of the Gorges" distributed by Department of Visual Education of the Methodist Church; full set of slide presentation would be 40 slides. (Box 15)